Testosterone placement has historically
been known for its role in treating
androgen deficiency, but I think there's
I think there's actually a place for it
that would be extremely beneficial
outside of merely just treating people
who actually have overt hypogonatism.
And in my opinion that that place that
testosterone would really shine are in
those people who are diabetic, those who
have high amounts of visceral atapost
tissue as well as people that are
classified as metabolic syndrome type
patients. What we know is that
testosterone does increase glucose
utilization. It increases insulin
sensitivity. It increases lipid
disposal. It upregulates your body's
metabolic processes in response to these
metabolic dysfunctions. But what the
newer literature is also showing us is
that metabolic dysfunction, diabetes,
obesity, those metabolic compromised
states actually negatively impact the
androgen receptor itself. There's
androgen receptors all throughout the
body. There's androgen receptors in the
pancreatic cells, pancreatic eyelet
cells. There's antino receptors in your
atapost tissue, your skeletal muscle,
your brain, they're practically scared
all throughout your body, your liver
tissue. And so when you are
metabolically compromised, when you're
obese, you have a high state of a lot of
reactive oxygen species. And reactive
oxygen species are produced by the
mitochondria of these respective cells.
Now when these cells are impacted
negatively such as a highly inflammatory
state for instance fatty liver disease,
obesity, diabetes, the mitochondria of
these respective cells in their
respective tissue, they no longer work
efficiently. Now if you don't know what
the mitochondria are, they're
essentially little bitty combustible
engines. They're like little bitty
lawnmower engines inside of these cells.
And as you age, their ability slowly
declines. Now, if you metabolically
compromise them, well, you're going to
compromise their ability to perform even
worse. This leads to more negative
consequences. But what we know is that
there's androgen receptors in all these
respective tissues. And androgen
receptor expression can actually
upregulate the mitochondrial activity of
the mitochondria in these respective
tissues. Even in people who are not
diabetic, merely introducing exogenous
testosterone to them can actually
increase their glucose utilization and
insulin sensitivity. We now know that if
you have someone who is overtly
diabetic, that's almost synonymous with
them needing to also be evaluated for
hypogonatism because the presentation of
low testosterone is now starting to
co-occur in the presentation of someone
who's metabolically compromised. There's
even more literature suggesting that
people who are diabetic overtly go ahead
just go ahead and screen them for low
testosterone because there's a high
probability they probably will have it
or do have it. I think there's a case to
be made for people who are clinically
overtly diabetic and some resistant. I
think you should actually go ahead and
treat them for an androgen deficiency. I
think you should actually consider them
a clinical candidate for exogenous
testosterone replacement therapy. I
mean, for for one, we know that having
one of those clinical conditions can
actually negate the benefits of their
own indogenous testosterone production.
And two, we also know that those
clinical conditions can also interfere
with their androgen receptors. So,
chances are they may not even be
responding to their own indogous
production of testosterone. So, I think
you should actually possibly go ahead
and consider them for TRT. And this is
even regardless despite what their
levels look like. Let's say you've got a
type two diabetic with high amounts of
visceral fat. We know they're very
metabolically
compromised and let's say what
hypothetically their testosterone 600.
So what? They're not responding to it.
Their receptors are not responding to
it. I truly do think there should be a
case for patients like this. You should
probably just go ahead and consider
treatment. And lastly, beyond
testosterone, we also know that there's
a similar relationship, similar role
with uh metabolic syndrome, type two
diabetes, as well as its relationship
with DHEAS. But that's beyond the scope
of this video. We'll talk about another
time. Thanks for watching.